<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short treatise of the quiet of the soul. How necessary a thing it is, and how it may be atttained [sic]. Composed by the reverend father John de Bovilla, an observant frier of the holy order of St. Francis. Permissu superiorum</title>
            <author>Bonilla, Jean de, 16th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3595BB</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229458</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895279</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895279</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152560</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77026)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152560)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2304:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short treatise of the quiet of the soul. How necessary a thing it is, and how it may be atttained [sic]. Composed by the reverend father John de Bovilla, an observant frier of the holy order of St. Francis. Permissu superiorum</title>
                  <author>Bonilla, Jean de, 16th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 58 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Juan de Bonilla. -- Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Peace of mind --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Soul --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spiritual life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152560:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152560:1"/>
            <head>A Short TREATISE of the QUIET of the SOUL.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the natural Conditions of our heart, and how it muſt be Governed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOU ought to know that God hath given you a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry noble heart, only cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated to love him; and in his love to be melted and conſumed: By his love you ſhall eaſily perform what you will, and being enamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with virtue, any difficulty ſhall be ſoon overcome: Whereas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152560:2"/>if by your own forces you attempt to do any thing, you ſhall effectuate nothing. Let the intention of your heart be well grounded, in ſuch ſort, that the exterior operation do proceed from the interior.</p>
               <p>And though penance and penal Exerciſes be laudable, when they be moderated with diſcretion an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the condition of the Perſons by whom they be wrought; yet very frequently the better part of them evaporate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vain complaiſance without any profit; wholly looſing your labor, unleſs they be Ruled and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by that which is interior.</p>
               <p>Mans life upon Earth is a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual warfare, as holy <hi>Job</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: In this War you muſt watch, and your watching muſt conſiſt in ſetling, purifying and quieting of your Spirit in all your motions. When any ſuddain ſtorm of paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſenſual unquietneſs ariſeth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152560:2"/>in your own Soul, be always ready with ſpeed to ſettle and pacify the ſame, in not granting it too much Liberty, to ſtart or wander out of the right way.</p>
               <p>Obſerve this ſo often as unqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs ſhall aſſault you, either in Prayer, or out of Prayer: Then ſhall you be able to pray well, when in this manner you know how to work well. And note, that when you practiſe the aforeſaid obſervation, you do it without force or violence, but rather with pleaſure: For your principal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe muſt be to quiet your Soul and Heart, and ſuffer them not to be diſordered, or to ſtray, but that always they be at reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152560:3"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the care which the Soul ought to have to ſettle her ſelf in quietneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHerefore before all things you are to place this peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Watchman and Guard over your ſenſes, and thereby without toil and travel you ſhall be led to great matters with great quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſecurity; by which quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſent by God Almighty, you ſhall Watch, Pray, Obey, and ſuffer injuries without oppoſition: Yet till you be ſatisfied in your ſelf, you are to ſuſtain ſome labor, for want of practiſe herein, but your Soul ſhall reſt quieted and comforted in whatſoever contradiction befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth you, and every day more and more your ſpirit ſhall be quieted: And if at any time you find your ſelf ſo afflicted that you cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152560:3"/>to this quietneſs, then have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to Prayer, wherein you muſt perſevere, after the example of our Saviour, who thrice prayed in the Garden, thereby to teach you, that all your refuge and truſt muſt be in Prayer; and depart not from it, till you find your Will conformable to Gods Will, being pacified, and repoſed.</p>
               <p>If you be imployed in ſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral work, force not your ſelf to make an end of it to ſoon, nor li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelf with any time, in which it muſt be finiſhed: But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther work the ſame with eaſe and tranquillity; for your principal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention muſt be to have God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eyes, with great quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without all kind of reſpect of contenting any other beſides him: For if you make any mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of other affections, you ſhall ſoon perceive the vexation and unquietneſs which in your Soul ſhall ariſe; ſo by falling down, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152560:4"/>riſing up again, you ſhall obſerve and clearly ſee that all your hurt proceedeth from ſelf-love, whilſt we endeavour that all things be done conformable to our will, and what otherwiſe falleth out, doth afflict, trouble and diſquiet us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>How this peaceable habitation may not be built on a ſuddain, but by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke care thou never ſuffer thy heart to be troubled, ſad, or altered, or mingled with any things which may diſquiet it, but labor always to keep it in peace; for our Lord ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed are the Peaceable:</hi> Which when you do, our Lord will build a peaceable City in your Soul, and make it his houſe of pleaſure. What he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of thee is only, that as often
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152560:4"/>as thou ſtandeſt up, thou ſhouldeſt ſit down again; (that is) keep thy ſelf quiet in all thy works, thoughts, and motions. And as in one day a City is not built, ſo thou muſt not think in one day to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to this peace and inward reſt, for it is our Lords building, and he himſelf muſt make thee his Houſe and Temple; otherwiſe thou doſt labour in vain. And ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that the principal Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this is Humility.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>How the Soul muſt deprive her ſelf of all comfort, for to attain to this quietneſs and peace.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr to enter in by this door of Humility, thou muſt be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to embrace tribulations, and eſteem them as thy ſiſters, and wiſh to be deſpiſed of all men,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152560:5"/>and that none do comfort thee but God: And let this be thy ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled perſwaſion, that only God is thy total Joy, and that all other things be Thorns to thee: So that thou art to accuſtom thy Soul to be alone with God, repreſenting unto thy ſelf, that if thou wert led to a place where thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt receive ſome diſgrace and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, thou wouldeſt go willingly and with joy to ſuffer it, being ſure that God is with thee; and to wiſh or deſire no other honor than to do that which is to his Honor and Glory, and to ſuffer for his Love. Thou muſt alſo force thy ſelf to be glad when any one treateth thee with injurious words, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth or rebuketh thee; for under this Cover, rugged as the Bark of a Tree, lieth hid a great Treaſure. Tribulation well ſuffered is a ſort of Soap, that waſheth out all the dregs of our imperfections and offences.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152560:5"/>
               <p>Finally, thou art not to ſeek for Honor, nor yet that any love thee in this life, nor make an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of thee: But if thou ſuffereſt with Chriſt Crucified, beware of thy ſelf as of an Enemy; follow not thy own Will, Judgments or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, if thou wilt not be caſt away. To this purpoſe thou muſt be armed; <hi>viz.</hi> for to defend thy ſelf againſt thy ſelf.</p>
               <p>Where thy will deſireth to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to any thing, although it ſeem very Holy, yet repreſent this with a profound Humility before our Lord, beſeeching him that his Will may be done in thee. And let this be done with a hearty deſire, without any mixture of ſelf-love, acknowledging thy ſmall forces, and how eaſily thou mayeſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by thy own opinions, that are ſhadowed with the ſhape of Holineſs, and indiſcreet Zeal: Of which our Saviour ſaith, <q>
                     <hi>Beware of the falſe Prophets, that come in ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skins,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152560:6"/>and are ravening Wolves: By their fruits you ſhall know them.</hi>
                  </q> Their fruits therefore are to leave behind them in the Soul vexations, and unquietneſs.</p>
               <p>Any thing that ſeparateth us from Humility, and this inward peace and quietneſs, under what color ſoever it be, it is a falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and a ravening Wolf; for under the ſhape of a Sheep it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to rob and deprive us of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and the quietneſs which is altogether neceſſary to him who intendeth to profit: And it ſo falleth out, that what hath been gotten in many days, and with much labor, is in little time loſt and ſtolen by theſe Wolves; and the more appearence any thing ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth of Holineſs, the better alſo muſt it be examined, and with greater reſt and inward quietneſs, as already hath bin ſaid.</p>
               <p>And note, that if at any time thou chance to fail in theſe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152560:6"/>be not therefore troubled, but humble thy ſelf in the Preſence of our Lord, and acknowledg thy weakneſs, and be adviſed againſt ſome other occaſion: For it may be our Lord permitted it ſhould ſo fall out, to abate ſome ſecret Pride which is in thee, unknown to thy ſelf. And if at any time ſome ſparks of vice do touch thy Soul, be not therefore troubled, but vigilantly watch, and ſweetly draw thy Spirit aſide; and ſettle it in quietneſs, in ſuch ſort that thou be not troubled, or altered, neither overjoyful, nor heavy; but keep thy Soul peaceably, and clean to God, whom thou ſhalt find within thy ſelf; aſſuring thee that the Divine intention ſeeketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but thy profit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152560:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>How the Soul muſt keep it ſelf in a ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarineſs; that God may work in it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THou muſt make great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of thy Soul, ſith it is the Temple in which God doth lodge and remain. Make ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it, that thou ſuffer it not to be mingled with any other thing. Let thy attendance to our Lords coming be in ſolitarineſs; for alone he deſireth to find thee, alone without thoughts, alone without wiſhes or deſires, alone e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven without thy own Will. Seek not indiſcreetly, but with the Council of thy Ghoſtly Father, for Croſſes, to ſuffer for God; but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thy ſelf rather to ſuffer for his Love what pleaſeth him. Do not thy Will, but Gods will be done in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152560:7"/>thee. Let thy Will be free, and united on all ſides: My meaning is, that thou deſire nothing; and if thou deſireſt any thing, deſire it in that manner, that if it take not effect, thou be not therefore affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; but that thy Spirit remain as quiet as if thou deſiredſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: Therein conſiſteth true li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, that one be not tied to any thing. God expecteth to find thy Soul alone, to work in it his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <p>O Solitarineſs, in which is build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the high City of <hi>Jeruſalem!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Deſert of Joy! O Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs wherein with great felicity we may enjoy the Almighty!</p>
               <p>Set not thy ſelf to reſt in this paſſage. Take off thy Shooes and enter, for the Land is Holy.</p>
               <p>Stay not to ſalute any Body by the way. Let the dead Bury the dead: For thou goeſt towards the Land of the living; Death hath no part in thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152560:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of the Prudence that muſt be uſed in loving our Neighbor, to the end this Peace be not interrupted.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>EXperience will teach thee, that this is the manifeſt way to life everlaſting: For the love of God and thy Neighbor ſhall be poured into thy Soul. <q>
                     <hi>I came,</hi> ſaith our Lord, <hi>to kindle fire on Earth, and my Will is that it burn.</hi>
                  </q> Although the Love of God hath no limits, yet the Love of our Neighbor hath, in which Moderation is to be uſed: For if you be not mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and adviſed, it will be your deſtruction; and by endeavoring to edify others, thou ſhalt caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy ſelf. So thou muſt love thy Neighbor, that thy own Soul ſuffer no danger or damage. Do not any thing only with that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152560:8"/>to give example to another, or for to gain others: For hereby thou ſhall not reap much unto thy ſelf. Do all things ſimply and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, to pleaſe God Almighty in them, without any other regard. Think humbly of thy ſelf in all thy works, and then thou ſhalt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how little thou art able to benefit others by them. See that thy Zeal of gaining Souls be not ſuch, that thou come thereby to loſe thy peace and quietneſs. Be thirſty and deſirous that all men come to know the truth, which thou doſt know, and that they be drunk with the Wine which God promiſeth all men, and giveth good cheap. This thirſt of thy Neighbors health thou muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain when thou haſt received it from our Lord; and not when thou haſt procured it by thine own diligence and indiſcreet Zeal: For being planted in the ſolitude of thy heart and Soul by the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152560:9"/>he will gather the fruit when it ſhall pleaſe him. In the mean while ſee that thou ſow nothing, but only keep thy Soul always ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary, and tending towards God: For God willingly findeth the Soul ſolitary and looſe on every ſide, thereby to bind and tie it the ſtronger to himſelf. Suffer thou thy ſelf to be tied, and diſpoſe thy ſelf to ſit idle in the quietneſs of thy Spirit, attending him which will come to hire thee, Caſt off all cares, and walk alone and free on every ſide, to the end that God apparel thy Nakedneſs with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and thereby thou ſhalt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the felicity which thou canſt not imagine; and having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got thy ſelf, his love only will live in thy Soul.</p>
               <p>In concluſion, with all diligence (or rather without all diligence, which may diſturb or diſquiet thy peace,) thou muſt pacify thy zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous intentions with great mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152560:9"/>whilſt God preſerveth in thee all peace and tranquility: For ſuch ſilence is more effectual than loud crying, and by this want of care, all is provided and procured, that we would have, which in ſubſtance is nothing elſe but a whole delivery of the Soul to God, being abſtracted from all other things, wherein thou muſt beware to think that of thy ſelf thou art able to do any thing; for it is God that muſt perform all, who requireth nothing elſe of thee towards this ſilence than that thou think humbly of thy ſelf in his preſence, and that thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to him thy Soul, ſeparated and abſtracted from all Worldly things, with an inward hearty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that Gods Holy Will be done, and perfectly fulfilled in thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:152560:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>How free from all ſelf-deſires the Soul ought to preſent her ſelf in the ſight of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN this manner thou muſt begin by little and little, with Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Reverence, and Hope in the ſame Lord, who calleth thee, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <q>
                     <hi>Come to me all ye that labor, and I will refreſh you:</hi>
                  </q> And in another place; <q>
                     <hi>All ye that be thirſty, come to the Fountains of Water.</hi>
                  </q> This moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Divine vocation thou muſt always follow, not precipitating your ſelf by preventing or running before the inſpirations of the Holy Ghoſt; for it is he who muſt take you by the hand and guide you, and then you ſhall be carried where the Waves of all Mercy flowing from the Sea of God's ſweet Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will carry you. When thou
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152560:10"/>art come thus far, then labour with all poſſible diligence, as well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as outward aſſurance, to draw near with all the powers of thy Soul, to think on ſuch things as make God Almighty worthy of praiſe, love, and to be deſired; and ſee that herein thou uſe no force to thy heart in ſuch ſort, that thou ſhouldeſt harden it, for that would be a great impediment of attaining to quietneſs, or diſpoſing thy ſelf to it. Follow my counſel, and exerciſe thy ſelf always, (and once again I ſay always,) both by will and by effect in the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God's Goodneſs, and of his continual loving Benefits: And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive with all Humility ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences as from his ineſtimable goodneſs ſhall fall upon thy Soul. Beware thou procure no Tears or other ſenſual Devotions, uſing force to thy heart; but rather qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et thy ſelf in this inward ſolitude. attending only that the Will of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152560:11"/>God may be accompliſhed in thee, and when he pleaſeth to ſend thee Tears they ſhall come without any force, but rather with ſweetneſs and tranquility, and then admit them with great Humility, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God's work in thee. And know that thou ſhalt endure loſs, if of thy ſelf thou preſume to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to any thing.</p>
               <p>This is my firſt and laſt adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement, and the Maſter-key of all this matter, <hi>viz.</hi> That thou learn to renounce thy ſelf, and to ſit thee down at the feet of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or with <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> hearkning what he ſaid to thy heart; and not be buſied with <hi>Martha,</hi> which is thy Body. Beware that thy Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, (of which thou art the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thy ſelf) do not hinder thee in this Holy Silence. Be well advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that when the wings of thy meditations and affections tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport thee to a deſire of union with God, and to a full repoſe in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152560:11"/>him that thou limit him not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſtraitneſs of certain compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, drawn from finite or ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Objects; for he is above all compariſons, being infinite in all places, and in all things, and all things are in him. Thou art to conſider an incomprehenſible Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſity, altogether infinite, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether admirable. Such are to be thy conſiderations, or admirations.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe thou muſt believe, that he is every where to be found, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven within thy own Soul, when thou lookeſt for him there: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his only pleaſure is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with the Children of men, thereby to make us worthy of himſelf, he having no need of us. This truth being found out by the light of thy Underſtanding, let thy Will reſt therein, with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid quietneſs.</p>
               <p>In thy Meditations, or Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, prefix not thy ſelf a Task, or number, in ſuch ſort that thou
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152560:12"/>be tied to do, think, or pray ſo much, or thus much; but let thy heart be free, to the end that where thou findeſt repoſe, there thou reſt to enjoy the ſweetneſs of our Lord, to what part ſoever of thy exerciſe he be pleaſed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate himſelf: And though thereby it fall out that thou doſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit what thou haſt ordained to do, be not troubled therefore, but without any fear: For that the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and enjoying of God, and the embracing of him in our arms is the end of this Exerciſe: To which when one doth attain, then the means ordained thereunto muſt needs ceaſe; and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo contrary to the true peace and quietneſs, as the care which one taketh while he work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in tying the Spirit by force to finiſh this or that; nor permitting God Almighty to lead the Spirit what way he pleaſeth, but that of neceſſity it muſt go on the way
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152560:12"/>that man hath imagined, eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more therein the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his own Will than the Will of God; which in effect is nothing elſe than in ſeeking for God to ſhun him, and endeavoring to pleaſe him, not to do his Will. Wherefore if truly thou deſireſt to advance thy ſelf in this way, and to attain to thy wiſhed end, intend or attend not to any other thing than to find God, who whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he be pleaſed to manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto thee, remain there with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paſſing any further, until he grant thee leave; forgetting with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al that there is any thing elſe in the World, whereof thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt think, or take care, ſaving on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of reſting in God. But when his Divine Majeſty is pleaſed to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw or abſent himſelf; then to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the finding of him out thou may'ſt return to thy Exerciſes, with the ſame purpoſe to find out by them thy beloved, whom when
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152560:13"/>thou haſt found again, obſerve what hath been ſaid of omitting all other things; becauſe thou haſt attained to what thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt have.</p>
               <p>Mark this point well, for many ſpiritual Perſons are caſt away, and much endamaged, in their progreſs, and quietneſs of Spirit, by being wearied, and as it were ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with their Exerciſes, eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves to have done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing if they finiſh them not, and placing therein their perfection: So reſerving to themſelves the propriety of their own Wills, and living a weary life of Hierlings, never attaining to the inward peace and quietneſs, in which our Lord doth truly remain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:152560:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of the Faith, wherewith we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Bleſſed Sacrament, and how a Man muſt offer himſelf to God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THou muſt endeavor every day more and more to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in thy Soul the faith of the Bleſſed Sacrament; and never ceaſe to admire ſo incomprehenſible a Myſtery; and rejoyce thy ſelf by conſidering how God doth exhibit himſelf under the common Forms of Bread and Wine; reverently obſerve how he abaſeth himſelf to exalt thee, and by his Humility worketh thy Glory. <hi>O bleſſed be they who believe, and ſee not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seek not that he ſhew himſelf to thee in any other manner, than as he doth under the Vail of the accidents: Draw near unto him, to the end his Divine Majeſty do
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152560:14"/>convert thee into himſelf, and not that thou convert him to thy ſelf. Endeavor to enflame thy Will in him, and that he enflame thee in his Love, and teach thee his holy Will.</p>
               <p>Always when thou doſt enter into this Holy Sanctuary, thou muſt be reſolved and ready to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for his Love all torments and injuries that may befal thee: Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all dryneſs of Spirit, or want of Devotion in Prayer, or out of Prayer, for ſuch ſhall often befal thee, all which thou muſt accept for good; (but take heed thou be not the cauſe of them) embracing and eſteeming them as thy Siſters; and thy only joy muſt be to ſuffer with thy beloved, and for his love be not unconſtant in that which thou beginneſt; but when thou art entred in theſe holy Exerciſes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main firm in thy Reſolutions, and advance in the way of ſweetneſs and peace, of which the more
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152560:14"/>thou takeſt, the more thou wilt deſire; Inſomuch that thou ſhalt not be able to live without this peace; it will ſeem an intollerable torment unto thee to be out of this quietneſs for an hour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>That the Soul muſt not ſeek any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort or delight, but in God alone.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THOU muſt always make choice of afflictions, and be glad to be there where leaſt Friendſhip is ſhewed unto thee, and where thou art to be moſt in ſubjection. Finally all things are to ſerve thee as occaſions of going forward towards God, ſo that nothing ſtay thee from advancing thy ſelf in this way, and in this thou muſt rejoyce, that all things ſeem troubleſome unto thee, to the end our Lord be thy content, in whom thou muſt always reſt.</p>
               <p>Addreſs all thy Labors to thy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152560:15"/>Lord, who is Mediator between God and Man. Love this Lord, and impart thy heart freely unto him, for he will reſolve thy doubts, and will lift thee up when thou ſhalt fall; he will abſolve, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate thee ſpiritually, when thou makeſt thy ſelf ready; for he is an Eternal Prieſt: When thy Ghoſtly Father ſhall caſt thee off, and will not Miniſter thee the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments as often as thou deſireſt, come then thirſty unto this Lord, who though he hath given Power to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> yet hath not deprived himſelf of the ſame: He will grant thee a Jubilee ſo often as thou doſt come unto him; and finally if thou doſt love him, thou ſhalt want nothing.</p>
               <p>Offer thy ſelf to God as a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in all peace and quietneſs of Spirit. And to the end thou go the better in this way, and that thou paſs over this journey with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out heavineſs or wearineſs, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152560:15"/>thou make ready thy Soul at every ſtep by enlarging thy Will, and making it fit that Gods Holy Will be fulfilled in thee; for if thou haſt a great deal of room to hold much, thou ſhalt receive much. And let thy purpoſe be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by works, to the end it befall not thee as it befel St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who reſolutely ſaid that he would die with Chriſt, but failed very ſoon, for that his determination came from himſelf, and from his own Will, and deſire; which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be good, (as in this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample it was) yet it is dangerous, and the beginning of a great fall, if our Will begin to think or deſire any thing without the help of God, Deſire always, and yet deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; that is, let thy deſire and Will be free on every ſide, as alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy we have ſaid; and as I ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, always and upon every occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, determine with thy ſelf with all thy forces, to be conformable
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152560:16"/>with God; and never determine with thy ſelf in any thing which is not to be done in that inſtant in which thou workeſt; but keep thy ſelf at Liberty.</p>
               <p>Yet note hereby, that none are forbidden to uſe a prudent care in things neceſſary and belonging to their ſtate; for that operation is in God and according to God; and thereby the peace, and the true ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual profit is not hindred.</p>
               <p>In all things purpoſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſpeedily what by thy ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly may be done, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly deſire nothing.</p>
               <p>In this preſent Inſtant, what thou art to do, is nothing elſe but to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thy will to God, and further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more to deſire or ſeek nothing: Be like unto a poor man, who of himſelf knoweth he is unable, and thou ſhalt always be joyful.</p>
               <p>To conclude. This Liberty of Spirit is the Key of thy perfection and perſeverance, which in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152560:16"/>is nothing elſe, than that the inward man doth conſiſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelf, and that he enlarge not himſelf to wiſh, deſire or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure any outward thing; and ſo long as one ſhall remain in this manner, he ſhall enjoy a Divine, and pleaſant Bondage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>That the Soul muſt not be diſmayed though it find reſiſtance in it ſelf, or diſturbance of this Quietneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COnſider that full often not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thy Pious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor in this matter, thou ſhalt find thy ſelf troubled, and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of this Solitarineſs, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and that the Whirlwind of thy own paſſions will raiſe up the duſt of unquietneſs, and trouble in thy Soul; which our Lord ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth for our greater good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that a Dew from Heaven
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152560:17"/>ſhall be ſent thee, by which the dry land of thy heart ſhall be fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and not only the duſt ſhall be laid thereby, but alſo flowers of a new and fragrant odor ſhall ſpring up, by which every day thou ſhalt be made more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and more pleaſing to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. This is the battel in which the Saints gained Crowns and great rewards. Whenſoever thou art troubled do but ſay,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Lord, Loe here thy Servant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thy will be done in me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I believe, O Lord, that thy Word ſhall never fail, and therein I only truſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Behold me; Therefore here do with me what thou wilt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I ſtand wholy at thy diſpoſition.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Bleſſed is the Soul that offereth it ſelf in this manner, in time of tribulation, as a Sacrifice to God.</p>
               <p>If this battel do laſt, or conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue for any long time, and thou canſt not conform thy ſelf to the Will of God ſo ſoon as thou
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152560:17"/>wouldeſt wiſh; be not therefore diſmayed, for that this is the Croſs which Chriſt will have thee to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and follow him; according to the example which in himſelf he hath ſhewed to thee; to which ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, conſider, if it pleaſe thee, the battel which Chriſt fought in the garden, when his Humanity ſhrunk; and ſaid, <q>
                     <hi>Father if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible let this Challice paſs from me.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But he preſently called his Soul to his ſelf, (for Chriſts deſire was free, and not tied at all to his own Will,) and ſaid with a profound Humility. <hi>Yet thy Will be done and not mine.</hi> Theſe be the Labors and Combats, which we muſt learn, by Chriſt our pattern, who did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf as an Example to us. Be not diſmayed, though often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thou wiſh to be rid, and free from theſe toils, but continue in Humility and Prayer, until thou come to loſe thy own Will, and that Gods Will be fulfilled in thee.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152560:18"/>Labor earneſtly, that no other thing (having only God) do Lodge in thy Soul, though it were for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſhort a time; let nothing at all ſeem better unto thee, nor ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve other mens malices, or evils; but paſs through all things like a Child, without grief or irkſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and without any hurt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>How diligent the Devil is to deprive us of this Quietneſs: And contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, we muſt beware of his craft.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OUR adverſary the Devil, his faſhion is to ſeek out for ſuch as he may ſwallow; and therefore he expecteth nothing rather of thee, than that thou foregoeſt both Humility, and Simplicity, and that thou attribute ſomething to thy ſelf, to thy own induſtry and endeavor; and that thou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemeſt others as inferior to thy ſelf, in diligence, and diſpoſing of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152560:18"/>themſelves to receive God's Gifts: Whereby thou mayſt come to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe ſome body, or other, in thy own thoughts: For by this means he will eaſily find a paſſage to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Soul; the Door by which he deſireth to enter in, is that of our own-ſelf eſtimation. If thou be not therefore well adviſed in ſuch occurrences ſpeeedily to ſtep backwards to confound, pull down, and annihilate thy ſelf, (as already we have ſaid) thou ſhalt fall at length into the Phariſee's Pride; of whom mention is made in the Goſpel, that he boaſted much of his own goodneſs, and judged other men for bad. And if by this means the Devil come to take poſſeſſion of thy Will, he will be ſoon Lord over it, planting therein all kind of Vice, to thy great damage, and loſs. For which cauſe our Lord warneth us to Watch and Pray. Wherefore thou art to ſtand on thy Guard, to the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152560:19"/>end thy Adverſary deprive thee not of ſo great a treaſure, as is the peace and quietneſs of thy Soul: For that he laboureth much to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive thee of this reſt: And pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that thy Soul live in unquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, wherein he knoweth doth conſiſt all damage and perdition; becauſe a quiet Soul doth work with facility, it worketh much, and worketh well, perſevereth, and eaſily withſtandeth all impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments: Whereas contrarywiſe the Soul which is troubled, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet, worketh but a little, and that little very imperfectly; it is ſoon wearied, and finally endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth an unprofitable martyrdom.</p>
               <p>If therefore thou deſireſt to gain the victory, and that the Enemy hinder not the profit of thy hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, be advertiſed before all things, not to ſuffer any tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to enter into your Soul, (nor be diſquieted) though it were but for a Moment. And to the end
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152560:19"/>thou mayſt the better look to thy ſelf, and beware of the Devils de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, hold it for a certain rule in this matter; That any thought that ſeparateth from the greater love of God, or greater hope in him, is as a Meſſenger from Hell; and as ſuch, thou muſt not admit him, but with all ſpeed thou oughteſt to drive him away, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the function of the Holy Ghoſt, is always to draw ſouls nearer and nearer to God, infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them in his love, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in them new Hopes: And the Devil worketh always contrary unto this; uſing all poſſible means to effectuate his own deſignments, which is againſt this: As for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, when he goeth about to breed fear in us; he aggravateth exceſſively our ordinary imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; giving us to underſtand, that our Soul prepareth not it ſelf as it ought to confeſs, communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and Pray: Whereby a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfulneſs
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152560:20"/>is raiſed in the Soul and alſo trouble, and fear.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe he procureth us to take impatiently the want of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, or delectation in Prayer, or other Exerciſes; giving us to underſtand, that our labor is loſt therein; and that it were better to forbear the performing of ſuch Exerciſes. Finally he worketh ſuch unquietneſs and diſtruſtfulneſs in the Soul, that it thinketh all what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is done to be to no profit or purpoſe, whereby great fear and diſcomfort is increaſed in ſuch ſort that the Soul thinketh it ſelf to be forgotten of the Almighty; which indeed is not ſo, but whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary; for the benefit which comes unto us by theſe drineſſes and want of Devotion, are innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable, if we could but conſider Gods purpoſe therein, requiring only at our hands, and for our part that we be patient, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in working; for as St. <hi>Gregory</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:152560:20"/>ſaith; <q>
                     <hi>God is much pleaſed by the prayer which is made by faith, and hope.</hi>
                  </q> Being alſo continued with a true fidelity, though the Soul therein be dry, and deprived of all delectation; and though the Soul be diſtracted, and as it ſhould ſeem, cannot produce one good thought; it is not therefore that the Prayer is loſt: For that the very tribulation born with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is a good Prayer, and obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth much in the ſight of God, and the bitterneſs of affliction doth ſhine bright before God. And as the ſame St. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith: Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, (or as we may ſay) inforceth God to favour us more than any other Exerciſe. Whereof it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that no good work is to be omitted, how deſtitute of devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or unquiet ſoever the Soul findeth it ſelf; for the omitting of it ſhould be nothing elſe, than to accord to what the Devil would
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152560:21"/>have, and to deprive the Soul it ſelf of wonderful benefits.</p>
               <p>To the end this be the better underſtood, and that the thing that is good, and profitable of it ſelf be not hurtful unto any, for the want of underſtanding; we will lay down briefly the benefits which we receive by the humble continuance of theſe ſteril and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavory Exerciſes, that having un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the matter well, it befal not that by them we ſhould leave our quietneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>How the Soul ought not to be diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for inward Temptations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>INfinite great good doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the Soul by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid indevotions, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al drineſs, if they be born with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and Humility, which if the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152560:21"/>Soul did once underſtand, it would not ſo much be diſquieted, or afflicted by them. And though there were no other conſideration to commend them unto us; yet this only ought to ſuffice, That or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, God ſendeth them, not to the end they ſhould be an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of heavineſs or diſcomfort unto us, but rather of joy and gladneſs, ſo that we ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them not as arguments of our Lords hate or diſlike of us, but rather of his great Love. And therefore we ſhould accept of them, as a ſpecial favour done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us.</p>
               <p>The truth hereof ſhall appear very manifeſtly if we do but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that ſuch accidents do not befal to others, than ſuch as eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially apply themſelves to Gods ſervice, and do ſeperate themſelves from all occaſions, which may of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him: For we never ſee that great ſinners, or ſuch as be much
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152560:22"/>addicted to this World, do make account or complain of ſuch Temptations; ſo that it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth manifeſtly, that it is the fruit by which God inviteth ſuch as he loveth well; and though it ſeem unſavory, and that the Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelf be very foul, yet there iſſueth from it a wonderful great profit unawares to us: Even though the Temptation be ſuch, whoſe only imagination may aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh or ſcandalize us, becauſe the more horrible and foul the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation is, the more alſo ſhall it terrify, afflict and make us hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſerve to the purpoſe which God intendeth, though as then the Soul doth not under ſtand it ſo, and therefore abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſame, and is loath to walk in that ſame way, becauſe it would not willingly be deprived of delectation and comfort; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming that what is done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, is but loſs of time and pains taken in vain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:152560:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>How our Lord ſuffereth theſe Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to come upon us for our good.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAnkind is ſo naturally Proud, Ambitious and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to its own Opinion, as if we did challenge it by inheritance from our Father <hi>Adam,</hi> who by a ſad Example, fell from the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which was due to Almighty God, whereof it proceedeth, that always we preſume more of our ſelves than we are in effect. This our ſelf-eſtimation is ſo noiſom towards our true ſpiritual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, that the only ſmell or ſmoak of it, is able to hinder us from true perfection; and becauſe it is ſo dangerous, our beſt Friend and good Lord hath a care of keeping us in that plight, by which we may always eſcape the danger, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152560:23"/>as it were of neceſſity, come to hold the true knowledge of our ſelves: As he hath done with the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter,</hi> by ſuffering him to fall into the denial of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that thereby he may come to know himſelf, and not to preſume any more. And God did ſend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Holy Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> a troubleſome Temptation of the fleſh, that thereby acknowledging his own infirmity, he ſhould think humbly of himſelf; to the end that Gods manifold revelations exhibited unto him, ſhould not puff him up into Pride, (as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf witneſſeth.) By which we ſee that our Lord taking pity on our miſery and perverſe inclination, doth ſuffer both horrible, foul and ſundry Temptations to aſſault us, to the end, that by them we may be made humble and careful of our ſelves, though in our own O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion we profit nothing by them; wherein his great Wiſdom and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152560:23"/>Goodneſs doth appear, by procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our greateſt good, by that which we think to be our greateſt hurt. For hereby we attain to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, (which is the only vertue we have moſt need of) for that it hapneth ordinarily, that he who feeleth the ſaid thoughts, and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit, with want of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, perſwadeth himſelf it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from his own great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, and that no true Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God could have ſuch a diſtempered Soul, or ſerve God with ſuch coldneſs and remiſneſs as himſelf doth, and thinketh that the like thoughts befal only to ſuch as be forlorn, whereof it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that he who a little before, rather eſteemed himſelf ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, now by this Phyſick ſent him from Heaven holdeth himſelf the worſt Creature of the whole World, and unworthy to bear the Name of a Chriſtian; to which ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and profound Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152560:24"/>the Soul would never attain to, if that the great Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of the horrible and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Temptations did not force it thereunto. Wherein God Almighty doth a ſingular favor in this life to the Soul. which he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in need of the like Phyſick.</p>
               <p>Beſides the aforeſaid benefits which ſuch Temptations and want of Devotion do work in the Soul, many other benefits do alſo fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: For the afflicted Perſon by theſe means is in a manner forced to make his recourſe unto God, and ask him ſuch vertues as may remedy his torments.</p>
               <p>Furthermore to the end he may be rid of the Martyrdom which his Soul doth ſuffer, he judgeth it expedient to eſchew all kind of ſin, and what may ſeem imperfect; wherein the Tribulation which firſt ſeemed to have cauſed his hurt, ſerveth for a ſpur to ſet him forward with fervor to find God,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152560:24"/>and ſeparate himſelf from any thing which he may think not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to his Divine pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Finally, the toil and Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Soul endureth in the ſaid Temptations and want of Devotion, is a Loving Purgatory, wherein it endeavoreth with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Humility: And it help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth towards the attaining of a great Crown of Glory in Heaven.</p>
               <p>Thus much I have ſaid, to the end it be underſtood, what ſmall occaſion we have to be troubled or ſad, for the want of Devotion, or for ſpiritual afflictions, as ſome Perſons of ſmall experience herein be troubled, which do attribute to the operation of the Devil, or to their ſins and imperfections, that which cometh from God, and do eſteem the tokens of love to be Arguments of hate, and do think theſe Divine favors, to be ſigns of forgetfulneſs, judging all their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor loſt, and without Merit, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152560:25"/>their loſſes to be without recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Whereas indeed they have loſt nothing, and thereof ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to receive theſe afflictions, as demonſtrations of Gods holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of them; which if they did but once well underſtand, they would not be diſquieted, or loſe their peace for enduring the like Temptations, or want of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion in Prayer, or other holy Exerciſes; but rather they would with a new perſeverance humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate their Souls in our Lords ſight, purpoſing in all and above all things to accompliſh his Holy Will, in what manner ſoever he be pleas'd to uſe them in this World; endeavoring to keep themſelves in peace and quietneſs, accepting of all things that befall them, as proceeding from the hands of the Loving Father of Heaven; ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring new thanks with inward joy, in place of ſadneſs and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, perſevering herein without
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152560:25"/>any loſs of time, until at length they attain to work with peace and reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Of the remedies the Soul may uſe, to the end it be not diſquieted by the faults and imperfections it hath.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF at any time thou chance to fall into any light offence, or negligence either in Works or Words; ſuch as to be angry at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that hapned to thee; to murmur, or hear others murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; to yield much to laughter, or other curioſity; to ſuſpect the worſt of others, or that by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means thou offend either once, or more often falling into the ſame fault, notwithſtanding thy purpoſe of taking heed from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling again; be not therefore trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, or diſcomforted, nor apply thy ſelf to treat of what is paſt with affliction; confounding thy
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152560:26"/>ſelf with new ſorrows and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and imagining with thy ſelf thou ſhalt never amend; thinking thou doſt not perform, or force thy ſelf as thou ſhouldeſt, which if thou hadſt done, thou ſhouldeſt not have fallen ſo often: Likewiſe conſidering the more thou purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt well, the more alſo doſt thou find thy ſelf inconſtant: Out of which cogitations, and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, do proceed great heavineſs and diſtruſt, and a Thouſand fears which overwhelm thy Soul; ſuch as be to deſpair of ever being rid of the ſaid imperfections; to think that thy own weak and unperfect determination cauſeth all thy hurt; Repreſenting to thy ſelf that thou doſt not ſerve God tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as thou oughteſt to do, by which means, confuſion and ſhame ſhall ſo much invade thee, that thou ſhalt not dare to addreſs thy ſelf to God, nor appear in his ſight for having carried thy ſelf unloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152560:26"/>towards him. Such Perſons as imploy themſelves in ſuch thoughts, do loſe much time there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, whilſt earneſtly they ſearch how long they ſtayed or remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and how far arrived their faults, if they conſented, and if wittingly, and willingly they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in them. And the more earneſtly they applyed themſelves to think thereof, the leſs they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand; and ſo become more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted: Out of which there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth a great perplexity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the confeſſing of their ſins, to which they come with fear, and after having confeſſed, yet they attain not to the quietneſs of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for that they will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelves to have confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wholly and entirely; ſo that they lead a miſerable life, bitter and unquiet, omitting to merit, and looſing great part of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:152560:27"/>
               <p>All this proceedeth from hence, that they conſider not their own natural imperfection, nor know not the manner how to negotiate with God Almighty, with whom (notwithſtanding their often falls into infirmities,) more is effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated with one loving Converſion, than with heavineſs and diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that proceedeth from an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſerious examination of faults, eſpecially if they be venial offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or ordinary. Such in the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of their unquietneſs ought to content themſelves with the opinion of ſome learned man, or their Ghoſtly Father.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, I add that the ſaid Loving Converſion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in God, is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and uſed in occaſions of Light and dayly ſins only; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of greater offences: If God do permit any to fall into them, not only once, but alſo more often, and though they be not commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152560:27"/>only by infirmity, but malice; becauſe that the contradiction of an unquiet Soul, and ſcrupulous, is not the means to reduce the Soul to a perfect eſtate; if it be not adjoyned to a lovely confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Gods goodneſs and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and this obſervation is parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly neceſſary for ſuch perſons, as do not only deſire to be rid of their miſeries, but alſo to profit in vertues and the Love of God. And becauſe many will not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it ſo, they go forward with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpiritual courage and hope, in ſuch ſort that they can ſcarce ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to any good thoughts. So they live a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table life, becauſe they follow their own imaginations, not hearkning to the true, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Doctrin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:152560:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>The manner how the Soul may quiet it ſelf in all occaſions, without loſs of time, or profit.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OBſerve therefore this Rule; ſo often as thou perceiveſt thy ſelf to have fallen into any defect, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great or ſmall; and though more than a thouſand times a day thou hadſt committed the ſame, even vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary, and without any urgent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion thereunto.</p>
               <p>Obſerve I ſay infallibly this Rule; That when thou ſeeſt thy ſelf fallen into any fault or defect; perſiſt not troubled, nor diſquieted in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration thereof, but ſtraitways with Confidence, and Humility in regard of thy own weakneſs, loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fix thy eyes upon God, and with thought and word ſay unto him.</p>
               <p>O Lord I have done like a ſinner as I am: And nothing elſe can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of me, than theſe and other ſuch faults. Neither only ſhould I have done this but much worſe and more if thou hadſt left me to my ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:152560:28"/>
               <p>I render thee infinite thanks, O Lord, I am heartily ſorry for what I have committed; pardon me, O Lord, for thy own ſelf, I beſeech thee, and grant me Grace that I do not offend thee any more.</p>
               <p>When thou haſt done this, loſe no more time in unquietneſs, doubting that our Lord hath not forgiven thee, but go forward in peace, and reſt with thy Exerciſes, in that manner, as if thou hadſt committed no error at all: And uſe this manner of opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at every time, and if need be at every moment, with the ſelf ſame quietneſs and confidence at the laſt time, as thou haſt in the firſt for that, beſides the particular Service done to God Almighty.</p>
               <p>This obſervation availeth for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thouſand good uſes; as namely, that thereby the Spiritual profit is not hindred. Time is not loſt in that which ſerveth to no purpoſe: And one getteth out of ſin with great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and Perfection.</p>
               <p>This point I could earneſtly wiſh that the diſquieted and afflicted Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons would but believe, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152560:29"/>which if they did, then ſhould they eaſily perceive the peace, and quietneſs of Spirit, from the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in which they themſelves walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, always loſing their time.</p>
               <p>Let not this ſeem much unto thee; for that it is the key of Spiritual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and the means by which in a little time it may be attained unto.</p>
               <p>There are wanting other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtructions for this Exerciſe, which afterwards may be given, when firſt good uſe is made of theſe: Let them be read with attention, and with deſire to benefit by them, which our Lord of his goodneſs will grant more than men can think or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
               <p>And it is to be noted, that this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe according to the Authors intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on expreſſed in the Prayer follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is not publiſhed for others, than ſuch as profeſs a courſe of life of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial progreſs in Vertue, and are far from giving themſelves over to dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſins; for unto ſuch as live careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, offending God Almighty grievouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon every light occaſion, this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy is to no purpoſe: Such I ſay
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152560:29"/>have juſt cauſe to be troubled and to bewail often their offences, and to have an eſpecial care in confeſſing them, to the end that by their negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence or careleſſneſs they be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of their due remedy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer to the Prince of Peace.</head>
               <p>O King of ſweetneſs, and God of Peace, I caſt my ſelf at your feet with all ſubmiſſion: Begging of your Majeſty, to ſpeak to me the Divine Word <hi>Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I humbly beg the true Peace, which is deſired of all: Beſtow that ſweet repoſe upon my Soul, which is its Center and Soveraign good; rally by your Authority the forces of my ſpirit diſtracted and tired by ſo many enemies who draw it from you; Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe all her diſquiets caus'd from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, whence ariſe all her miſeries.</p>
               <p>Your word, Soveraign Verity, is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged not to deny me, your Mercy and Juſtice have intereſt not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit theſe Wars betwixt my paſſions and reaſon, no more than betwixt you and me: Your Divine Empire appears more glorious in Peace and quietneſs than in confuſions and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:152560:30"/>
               <p>You do not call your ſelf the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, Prince, and Diſtributor of other things in the ſame ſtyle as you do of Peace, which your holy Angels who ſtudy in all things your Divine Will, publiſhed at your Birth, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd a Canticle of it ſurpaſſing all Songs of Triumphs or Victories.</p>
               <p>O my Saviour cauſe to flow in me the River of Peace, that Torrent of pleaſure, which your Prophets have ſo much ſpoken of; give me that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of peace, which you have ſo often beſtowed on your Friends, and which none can give but your ſelf: And ſince after your departure you have left it under the protection of your Holy Spirit, where can it be better lodg'd than in a Soul which is empty, and deſires nothing but to entertain it alone? I have great confidence in your Soveraign goodneſs, that you will not refuſe me, that my cries ſhall turn your eyes of mercy to aſſiſt me, that I be not numbred amongſt the impious, who have never known the way of Peace, nor never ſhall enjoy it, except they amend their wicked lives.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
